Finding Aid for St. Andrew’s Episcopal Church (Clawson, Mich.) records, 1951-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Andrew’s Episcopal Church (Clawson, Mich.) records 1951-2011
St. Andrew’s Episcopal Church (Clawson, Mich.).
7 linear feet
2011036 Ba 2
The records of St. Andrew’s Episcopal Church (Clawson, Mich.) document the history of the church from its beginning in 1951 to its closing in 2011. Records include church registers, parish directories, bulletins, newsletters, photographs, and other administrative records.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of the church were donated by the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan (donor no. 1059 ) in January 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
St. Andrew's Episcopal Church was founded in 1951 as a mission of St. John's Episcopal Church in Royal Oak. Rev. Henry Simpson, a retired priest of the Diocese of Michigan officiated a morning prayer service at Kenwood School in Clawson, which was attended by the group who would become the first congregation of St. Andrew's. The congregation would meet at the school until 1955 when the first of three structures which would house St. Andrew's was built. At that point Rev. Alex Newell had become vicar. In August of 1958 he was replaced by Rev. William O. Swan. Swan was then succeeded by Rev. Paul S. Hiyama, who remained for 15 years and became the first rector when St. Andrew's attained parish status in 1962.
The final church building with expansion was opened on Christmas Eve in 1963. Hiyama was replaced in July of 1964 by interim rector Rev. Howard S. Ebright. In August 1975 Reverend Edward J. Campbell was made rector and remained for 12 years. Rev. Harry T. Cook succeeded in Campbell in 1987. He was joined by Rev. E. Anne Kramer, Deacon, in a team ministry.
Saint Andrew's suffered financial difficulties towards the end of its existence. Cook retired in 2009, and the congregation was led briefly by Rev. Mark Jenkins and Fr. Bill Fleming, before its members voted to close the church in September of 2010. The final service was given on January 5, 2011, and was presided over by Bishop Wendell Gibbs of the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan.
Saint Andrew's Church created and kept many records which document the activities and membership of the church. The record group is divided into several series: Register of Church Services; Registers of Marriages, Baptisms, Confirmations, Burials, etc.; Vestry Records; Chronological Series; Church Bulletins; Church Newsletters; Parish Directories; Organizational Record Books; and Other Records. Photographs of members and events are scattered throughout the collection.
The records document both the administration and activities of the church. Of special interest to the genealogist are the Registers of Marriages, Baptisms, Confirmations, Burials, etc. These volumes contain dates and other information about members of the church parish. Other membership information will be found in the Parish Directory series. The Vestry Records contain minutes, reports, and other items related to the administration of the church. This series should be supplemented with the Chronological series which is made up of annual folders containing correspondence, reports, photographs, and other items from each year. For information on events and services of the church, researchers should examine the Church Bulletins and Church Newsletters. The run of newsletters is fairly complete but only a sampling of the bulletins were retained, enough to document every decade in the church's history.
Subjects:
Episcopal Church--Michigan--Clawson.; St. Andrew's Episcopal Church (Clawson, Mich.); Clawson (Mich.)--Church history.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Clawson.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Register of Church Services
  - October 14, 1951-December 24, 1961 (Box 1)
  - December 25, 1961-December 18, 1969 (Box 1)
  - December 21, 1969-July 4, 1978 (Box 1)
  - July 5, 1978-January 28, 1985 (Box 1)
  - January 29, 1985-November 14, 1991 (Box 1)
  - November 17, 1991-October 27, 1999 (Box 1)
  - October 31, 1999-January 5, 2011 (Box 1)
- Registers of Marriages, Baptisms, Confirmations, Burials, etc.
  - Canonical Parish Register
    - October 11, 1951-November 5, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Canonical Register of Baptisms
    - November 9, 1958-October 12, 1986 (Box 1)
    - November 2, 1986-May 30, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Canonical Register of Burials
    - March 26, 1967-December 19, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Canonical Register of Confirmations
    - March 9, 1958-December 17, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Canonical Register of Marriages
    - January 14, 1967-February 25, 1984 (Box 1)
    - May 5, 1984-June 5, 2004 (Box 1)
    - July 24, 2004-April 18, 2009 (Box 1)
- Vestry Records
  - Meeting Minutes
    - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - 1972-1981, 9 folders (Box 2)
    - 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 2007-2010 (Box 2)
      (include 1 CD in folder)
  - Correspondence and other records
    - 1963-1978 (Box 2)
- Chronological Series
  - 1951-1961, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 1962-1964 (Box 3)
  - 1966-1978, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - 1981-1998, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - 1999-2011, 5 folders (Box 4)
- Church Bulletins
  - 1952-1956 (Box 4)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 4)
  - 1964-1974, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1987 (Box 5)
  - 1991-1993 (Box 5)
  - 1997-2010, 14 folders (Box 5)
- Church Newsletters
  - 1955-1970, 7 folders (Box 5)
  - 1971-2010, 8 folders (Box 6)
- Parish Directories
  - 1959 (Box 6)
  - 1964 (Box 6)
  - 1966-1969 (Box 6)
    1968 directory contains photos of members
  - 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    1973 directory contains photos of members
  - 1975-1977 (Box 6)
    1976 directory contains photos of members
  - 1985-1989 (Box 6)
  - 1991-1995 (Box 6)
    1993 directory contains photos of members
  - 1997-2000 (Box 6)
  - 2002 (Box 6)
  - 2010 (Box 6)
  - Undated (Box 6)
- Organizational Record Books
  - Episcopal Churchwomen, Board Meeting Minutes 1964-1967 (Box 6)
  - Episcopal Churchwomen, Constitution and By-Laws 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - Minutes of the Chapel Committee 1954-1958 (Box 7)
  - Minutes of different meetings 1954-1961 (Box 7)
  - Remembrance Book, Memorials 1953-1994 (Box 7)
- Other Records
  - Application for Admission into Union with Protestant Episcopal Church in Diocese of Michigan 1961 (Box 7)
  - Board of Christian Education, By-Laws and Board Meeting Calendar 1970-1975 (Box 7)
  - Building and Architectural Design, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Clawson Ministerial Association Notes 1940-1968 (Box 7)
  - Fall Fair 1962-1992 (Box 7)
    includes some photos of events
  - Groundbreaking Events 1963, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1986-1996 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box 7)
  - Photographs of members and events, 1958-1993 (includes some negatives) (Box 7)
  - Other photos of Members and Events, undated (Box 7)
  - Sermons by Harry Cook 1997-2000 (Box 7)
  - Treasurer's Records 1965-1977 (Box 7)